Today's דף daf is דף מ"ג, daf Mem Gimmel, 43. We pick
up at the very bottom of מ"ב עמוד ב' Mem Bet Amud
Bet and we have, we're sort of on a little bit of
a digression which is only slightly, that the פסוק, pasuk, we're going
through דרשנ'ינג darshaning the פסוקים pesukim and the question is why does
it say והמית איש או אשה, vehemit ish o isha, which I
don't have written there, but after here it says כי יגח שור
איש או אשה ומת ki yigach shor ish o isha vamet and
it's וענוש כאשר נתפרש שם ve-unsh kashur kemetporsho sham והמית
איש או אשה. vehemit ish o isha. Why do you have to
repeat איש או אשה? ish o isha? And רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva
said it's to tell you that look, first, you know, the people
here are dead, so who are you paying the כופר kofer to?
You're paying it to the heirs, and the same way you would
pay it to the descendants of the man, you pay it to
the descendants of the woman. And the חידוש chidush there is you
don't pay it to the husband even though the husband normally inherits
his wife. So the גמרא Gemara says well it's because this debt
comes after the woman is dead, and therefore the husband only inherits
his wife in terms of money that she was had or was
entitled to, we'll see entitled to in a minute, when she was
alive, because that's when there was that bond, so then when she
died it passed on to him. But money she gets or becomes
entitled to after she died, there's no longer a bond with him,
it goes down to her heirs. Okay, she stipulated in a will
or something like that right? Yeah, but wills are different, well you
can't stipulate in a will something that's going to only come after
your death. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says here at the bottom
of מ"ב עמוד
ב', Mem Bet Amud Bet, ובנזיקין לא, ubenezikin lo, three lines from
the bottom, middle of the line or towards the end of the
line, ובנזיקין לא אמר רבי עקיבא, ubenezikin lo amar Rabi Akiva, where
would רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva say that a woman's heirs would not
collect normal damages which would be a debt incurred during life? So
if a woman was damaged and somebody owed her money or the
owner of the ox owed her money and then the woman died,
where would that money go? So what we've been saying now is
it logically it should go to the husband. But and רבי עקיבא
Rabi Akiva would agree that in that case it would go to
the husband, it wouldn't go to the heirs. But is that really
true? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, הכה את אשה
ויצאו ילדיה, hika et isha veyatz'u yeladeha,
the case in the תורה, Torah, a man smote a woman and
she miscarried. נותן נזק וצער לאשה ודמי ולדות לבעל. nosay nezek vetza'ar
le'isha udmei veladot leba'al.
So the נזק nezek and the צער tza'ar goes to the woman,
she's the one that actually suffered the injury and the pain. And
the rest of it too? And the rest of it too, right,
בושת, boshet, whatever, exactly. ודמי ולדות לבעל. udmei veladot leba'al.
But the one thing the תורה Torah makes clear is that the
payment for the fetus, that goes to the husband. Okay. אין הבעל,
ein haba'al,
now let's say the husband is no longer around when it comes
time to pay, he died, נותן ליורשיו, nosay leyorshav,
you give it to his heirs. Fine. אין האשה, ein ha'isha, if
the woman is not around, this should be נותן nosay not נותנת,
nosaint, נותן ליורשיה. nosay leyorsheha.
If the woman isn't around you give to her heirs. So here's
a case where a woman suffered injury in her life, she died,
and it says you give to her heirs and not to her
husband. What's that about? Okay, I mean it didn't say that this
is רבי עקיבא's Rabi Akiva's position, but we don't hear anybody arguing.
Okay. Now, היתה שפחה ונשתחררה, hayta shifcha venishtachrara,
let's say it was a different case, we're not going to focus
on this but this is the end of the ברייתא, Braita, about
a slave that was freed, או גיורת, o giyoret, or a woman
who had converted, and רש"י Rashi says and presuming that she basically
and that case she died, so in that case she died, she's
got no heirs. So what happens? So this is money that you
owe to a גר ger that now the גר ger is dead,
and even property a גר ger owned would be כל הקודם זכה,
kol hakodem zachah, nobody's to inherit, it's הפקר. hefker. So in this
case זכה, zachah, you get to keep the money that you owe.
Okay, anyway, we're not going to focus on that, but we have
the problem that why when the woman dies do you give it
to her heirs and not to the husband if it was a
debt incurred when she was alive. So אמר רבה בגרושה, amar Rabba
begerusha,
she's divorced. Okay, וכן אמר רב נחמן בגרושה, vechen amar Rav Nachman
begerusha, she's divorced. Okay, now we're going to have to ask a
question, when was she divorced? רש"י Rashi says at least initially we're
talking about that she got divorced after the injury occurred. Okay, when
the injury occurred then she was married, so you owed the דמי
ולדות demei veladot to the husband right, because that's what the תורה
Torah says, he was still the husband at that time. Afterwards they
got divorced and then so now you owe, you still owe, you
haven't paid up your debt, the נזק nezek and the צער tza'ar
to the woman. She dies. If she dies without being married then
her husband doesn't inherit, her heirs inherit. So it all makes sense.
Okay. The גמרא Gemara says אמי בגרושה נמי תפלוט בדמי ולדות, ammi
begerusha nami tiphlot bidmei veladot, one minute, if it was a case
of a גרושה gerusha why do you still pay the דמי ולדות
demei veladot to the husband? Right, the גמרא Gemara assumes here that
the reason the דמי ולדות demei veladot go to the husband is
somehow because it's sort of like somehow through the wife or because
it's a little
funny because מעשה ידיה. ma'aseh yadeha. But what? Something like that, something
like that. So meaning if the גמרא's Gemara's question was if the
נזק nezek occurred after the divorce, why do you pay to the
husband? That makes a lot of sense, he's out of the picture
after the divorce.
Why should that change who you owe the money to, right, if
they get divorced afterwards? But let's assume the גמרא's Gemara's question is
the נזק Nezek occurred after the divorce. So the נזק Nezek occurred
after the divorce, so the husband should be out of the picture.
Why do you owe the money to the husband? So אמרי, Amrei,
גרושה נמי תפלוג בדמי ולדות, gerusha nami tivlak b'dmei vlados, she should
get a portion of the דמי ולדות, dmei vlados, or the whole
thing. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, התורה זכתה דמי ולדות לבעל,
haTorah zachsta dmei vlados l'baal, the Torah awarded the דמי ולדות dmei
vlados to the husband, אפילו בא לביזנות, afilu ba l'beiznus,
he doesn't have to be the husband, he just has to be
the father, okay. So even if they had sex out of marriage,
right, so in this case they had sex in marriage, conceived in
marriage, and then got divorced. So, but even, and they just weren't
married at the time. But even if they had sex out of
the context of marriage, there was never marriage here, okay, nevertheless he
is still the father, and it is the father that gets the
דמי ולדות, dmei vlados, not the husband. Okay, so even if they
were divorced at the time of the נזק, Nezek, he gets the
דמי ולדות. dmei vlados. מאי טעמא, Mai taama, what's the reason? אמר
קרא, Amar kra, כאשר ישית עליו בעל האשה. ka'asher yashis alav baal
ha'isha.
It calls him the בעל. baal. It doesn't say, I mean, I
don't know what other words the Torah had actually, it couldn't say
איש האשה, ish ha'isha, okay, but since it uses the word בעל,
baal, which means בועל, boel, as a word that describes husband but
focuses on the act of sex, we understand that it means as
long as he was the one that had sex with this woman,
meaning and conceived the child, it was his child, he's awarded it
even if he's not the husband at the time of the נזק.
Nezek. Now you might wonder why that is. Now, well the question
is actually, you know, is the father more involved, you know, do
you always know? Well, I would say, I would say more than
that, you know, according to הלכה, Halacha, and I should have checked
this out
but I didn't, but I'll try to check it out and get
back to you. But according to הלכה Halacha the basic point is
that הלכה Halacha says in the case of divorce, let's say there
are already children. In the case of divorce, who does the הלכה
Halacha say the children go to? So the general rule is that
the הלכה Halacha says that the children go to the father unless
the children are very young, very young, like I forget up to
four or five or whatever, need the mother. Now later הלכה Halacha
developed to always basically say you keep in interest, it's the best
interest of the child, you know, sort of like adopting a דינא
דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina type of an approach. But according to
the, but the basic assumption had been that they're the fathers, welcome
to the patriarchy, right, it's אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, right,
the children are seen as the father's children. Okay, so that presumably
is also why the דמי ולדות dmei vlados are to the father.
So the question is what happens in a case of, you know,
a classic case of
a paternity suit, right, what would you have if somebody is the
father but they were never married? Are they also seen as fundamentally
his child? Right, I don't know the answer to that. Right, it's
one thing to say in the context of a patriarchy of a
legitimate child born in the context of marriage, they're seen fundamentally as
the father's children and not as the wife's children. But in a
case of conception outside of marriage, right, would it be the same?
I really don't know the הלכה Halacha about that. You're talking about
unborn children, so then you differentiate between a born child, which is
the patriarchy, and an unborn child, because you also have a concept
עובר ירך אמו הוא. ubar yerech imo hu. That's true. That's a
good point. That's a good point. So but but all the more
reason that this is a חידוש. chidush. This is both out of
wedlock and it's her own body, and we still see it as
you award the דמי ולדות dmei vlados to the father, not the
husband but to the biological father. So it's quite a חידוש chidush
and I do wonder what that case would be, that if it
wasn't a woman suing for support for you know for paternity but
it was the man suing for custody, right, in that case where
they had a child out of wedlock, I wonder if the same
assumption would play. But this is quite a shocking גמרא. Gemara. Now
if you want even more shocking look at תוספות, Tosfos, אפילו בא
לביזנות, afilu ba l'beiznus, תוספות Tosfos says ירושלמי בעי, Yerushalmi baei, רבי
עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, בא על אמו, ba al imo, בא על אחותו,
ba al achoso,
let's say the child is a ממזר, mamzer, he had sex with
a woman he couldn't marry. Okay, יכול אף בבעל ההריון, yachol af
b'baal haherayon, תלמוד לומר בעל, talmud lomar baal, אותו שראוי לקרות בעל,
oso sheraui likros baal, יצאו אלו שאינם ראויים לקרות בעל. yatzu elu
she'einam reuyim likros baal.
It'd have to be at least that it was possible for them
to have been a married couple. Okay, so it's the father but
not just the biological father in the case where it was possible
for them to be married. So that's a big חידוש chidush now
that the money goes even if they are not married, just it
goes to the biological father. Okay, but that's how we've explained why
if she's divorced, then she dies, the money passes on to the
heirs because she's not married to her husband anymore. Back to the
גמרא. Gemara. דנוקמה לרבה כגון שגבו מעות, denukma l'Rabba k'gon shegavu ma'os,
ולרב נחמן כגון שגבו קרקע. u'l'Rav Nachman k'gon shegavu karka.
The גמרא's Gemara's saying, one minute, it's now going to reference a
debate that we have elsewhere in בבא בתרא Bava Batra about a
question of when is something considered ראוי ra'ui or מוחזק. muchzak. And
this is... That's exactly the idea we used before a minute ago
for the husband. The principle is that a בכור, bechor, a firstborn,
gets double portion on the property that was already under the control
of the father when he died. But property that became came to
the father after he died, he does not get double portion. So
here would be an extreme example: the father had a lottery ticket,
and he won the lottery after he died. Okay, the בכור bechor
would not get a double portion. It was only money that was
under the father's control. Now let's say the father had a debt.
He had a credit, somebody owed him money, okay, and he had
the שטר, shtar, he just hadn't collected the debt yet. Would that
be and then the debt was collected or paid after the father
died, would the בכור bechor get double or not? Okay, so there's
a debate here whether it is between Rabbah and Rav Nachman, whether
the debt was paid with money or with land. So let's read
that. דאמר רבה גבו קרקע יש לו, D'amar Rabbah, gavu karka yesh
lo, if they collected land with that debt, then he is considered
to have been under the father's possession, even though it was only
collected after the father died, it was considered to have been under
the father's possession and the בכור bechor gets a double portion. גבו
מעות אין לו, Gavu ma'ot ein lo, but not money. And the
reason being, well, because you have a lien against land, land you
can't take away. We always knew the land was there. It's always
it's only in שטר shtar then? By שטר. shtar. So we always
exactly, so we always knew the land was there, and therefore even
when the father died, the debt hadn't been collected, it was like
it had been collected, there was a lien on the land and
nobody was stealing the land, the land wasn't going anywhere. But if
you got money, who knew you would have ever been able to
collect money off of this thing? And that's like something that's like
winning the lottery ticket, not exactly, but whatever, that wasn't considered already
in your possession. Okay, Rav Nachman says the reverse. גבו מעות יש
לו גבו קרקע אין לו. Gavu ma'ot yesh lo, gavu karka ein
lo. No, no, no. He says if you collect money now we're
talking specifically that it was a loan so Rav Nachman says if
you got you lent a hundred dollars and after the father died
he got back a hundred dollars, we view it as the same
hundred dollars. It's not literally the same hundred dollars, it's not the
same bills, okay, but since it was money that was lent and
money that was gotten back, you view it as money that was
always in the estate, okay, whereas if it was קרקע karka that
was collected, you know, that's that's like a whole other process, it
requires getting בית דין beis din involved, the whole thing, and clearly
it's something new. Okay, so anyway, that's the debate of whether the
בכור bechor would get פי שנים. pishnayim. Why is it relevant here?
Because we're assuming the same thing is true about the husband collecting
from his wife. Remember we said when money was owed to her
after she died, the כופר, kofer, he doesn't inherit it. The husband
only inherits his wife's property that was under her control at the
moment that she died. So here we have an exact case about
let's figure out what exactly constitutes under her control. She was damaged,
injured in her life. Money was owed to her. That money is
now going to get paid, right, after she died. Okay, because that's
what it says, the woman isn't around and now it's time to
pay the money. Well, according to Rabbah and Rav Nachman, based on
whether you pay cash or whether you pay קרקע karka should determine
whether you view it as if that money was always under her
control. So in the case where you're paying let's say קרקע karka
according to Rabbah and the money was now seen as always under
her control, you're right, the husband should inherit. Why did the ברייתא
braisa say her heirs inherit and not the husband? Because it was
paid in cash, it wasn't paid in קרקע. karka. So even though
the money was owed before she died, it's not considered to be
her money for the husband to inherit if it only gets paid
after her death and paid in a way that based on קרקע
karka or cash it's seen as new funds under her control and
not money that was always under her control. Yes. Basically, you never
address the question of do you have like an automatic lien on
the guy's property for this כופר kofer or is it just whatever
is מטלטלין? metaltelin? Well, in by normal נזק nezek you do have
an automatic lien, like it's מלוה הכתובה בתורה ככתובה
בשטר דמיא. milvah haksuvah batorah keksuvah b'shtar damya. By כופר kofer it
gets to the whole question of כופר כפרה kofer kaparah and I'm
not sure if it would be different or not, so I'd have
to check that. Okay, but so the גמרא Gemara anyway the גמרא
Gemara says, so look, yes it's true she was owed the money
and you were saying, "Oh, she was owed the money then it
should go to the husband." No, not just because she's owed the
money doesn't make it under her control. And it might depend between
Rabbah and Rav Nachman. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הני מילי לבני מערבא אליבא דרבנן. hani milei livnei maarava aliba d'rabanan.
That debate of Rabbah and Rav Nachman was a debate of based
on the בני מערבא bnei maarava according to the רבנן, rabanan, which
is like meaning a whole position in the גמרא Gemara in בבא
בתרא Bava Batra which we're not doing right now, but they were
debating within a certain position that said that fundamentally there's a problem
when you collect a loan that was not money yet under your
control, and therefore it's a question if the בכור bechor gets double.
כי קאמר הכא כרבי. Ki ka'amar hacha k'Rabbi. We're saying here according
to רבי. Rabbi. רבי Rabbi said whenever you collect a loan after
a death, it's like the money was always under the control and
the בכור bechor does get a double portion. So within the position
of רבי, Rabbi, that's our that's our question. רבי Rabbi assumes if
The money was owed during life, then even if it was paid
after death, it's considered like that money was always under the control
and the בכור bechor gets a double portion. And that's why we
wanted to know why would the woman's heirs get it if the
money was already owed under life? Okay? So you got the idea?
A husband inherits his wife if they are married at the time
of death and if the money is under her control at the
time of death. In the case of the כופר, kofer, that money
only becomes under her or only owed to her after, so the
husband doesn't inherit. In the case of divorce, so at the time
of the death they're not married, so the husband doesn't inherit. How
about money owed when they were... she was alive and paid after
her death? Okay, that's the last thing we're talking about. So according
to some opinions it might matter, did... was it paid with קרקע
karka or cash? And based on what it was paid with, it
would be considered either to have been under her control and the
husband would inherit or not under her control and the husband wouldn't
inherit. And that could have explained this ברייתא. braita. But according to
רבי, Rebbi, anything that was owed at life, even paid after death,
is always considered under her control and therefore always would go to
the husband. Okay, so those are the different possibilities within this issue
about the husband versus the wife's heirs inheriting her. Along the way
we had an interesting insight into the דמי ולדות dmei veladot that
it's not about being the husband, it's about being the father. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rav Shimon
ben Lakish, שור שהמית את העבד שלא בכוונה shor she-hemit et ha-eved
she-lo b'kavana פטור משלושים שקלים. patur mi-shloshim shekalim. Okay now here remember
I told you a while ago to think about whether the paying
of כופר kofer and stoning the ox have to come together. Can
you have a case if you don't stone the ox you would
still pay כופר? kofer? Now we actually had a case about that
just a little while ago, right? We were talking about when רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said to... whoever it was, רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
how could you be paying half if the ox is going to
get stoned? And רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said it was... הביאו לבית
דין ונשחטו? hevi'o l'veit din v'nishchitu? And רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says
no, no, it was נוגח שלא בכוונה, nogei'ach shelo b'kavana, tried to
kill an animal and killed a person. So that would have was
a scenario where you're not going to stone the ox but you're
still going to pay the כופר. kofer. Okay, or we had a
discussion before about a רגל שדרסה על גבי תינוק, regel she-darsa al
gabei tinok, right? Which wasn't בכוונה. b'kavana. So until now we've been
assuming you can have a case where you don't stone the ox
and if there's a death you're still pay כופר. kofer. Now we
are going to revisit that question and look at two cases. Number
one the שלושים של עבד, shloshim shel eved, you don't stone the
ox because as it says, right, אם עבד יגח השור או אמה
כסף שלושים שקלים יתן לאדוניו והשור יסקל. im eved yigach ha-shor o
ama kesef shloshim shekalim yitein l'adonav v'ha-shor yisakeil. No, no, normally you
do, but if you don't stone the ox would you pay the
שלושים של עבד? shloshim shel eved? And we're going to go back
and look at the case of כופר, kofer, which until now we've
been assuming they can become... they can become separate. What would be...
but now we're going to question that. If you don't pay the...
if you don't stone the ox in a scenario you don't stone
the ox would you still pay the כופר? kofer? Yes. Also... שור
האיצטדין, shor ha-itzitadin, right? Is... בכוונה, b'kavana, but we never directly addressed
whether you pay the כופר kofer by the שור האיצטדין, shor ha-itzitadin,
right? That was where I first raised that question, correct. So we
never addressed שור האיצטדין shor ha-itzitadin you don't... you don't stone, but
the גמרא Gemara never addressed the question would you pay כופר? kofer?
We would assume yes, but maybe it depends. If you made it
goad on somebody, I would hope the answer would be yes. If
somebody else did it then maybe you're an אונס oneis or something,
we never really... got to the bottom of that. So let's take
a look now at what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says. אמר רב
שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rav Shimon ben Lakish, שור שהמית את העבד
שלא בכוונה, shor she-hemit et ha-eved she-lo b'kavana, if we're dealing not
with the כופר kofer case but the שלושים של עבד shloshim shel
eved and you're not going to stone the ox because it's שלא
בכוונה, she-lo b'kavana, פטור משלושים שקלים, patur mi-shloshim shekalim, you're exempt. שנאמר,
כסף שלושים שקלים יתן לאדוניו והשור יסקל. Shene'emar Kesef Shloshim Shekalim Yitein
La'Adonav VeHaShor YiSakeil.
They are immediately juxtaposed. Pay the thirty and stone the ox. So
they've got to come together. כל זמן שהשור בסקילה הבעלים משלמים שלושים
שקלים. kol zman she-ha-shor b'sekila ha-be'alim meshalmim shloshim shekalim.
Whenever the... you're stoning the ox, you pay your thirty. אין השור
בסקילה אין הבעלים משלמים שלושים שקלים. ein ha-shor b'sekila ein ha-be'alim meshalmim
shloshim shekalim.
You're not going to pay your thirty. Now, I just want to
pause and ask us a question. If you had to decide of
the two,
כופר kofer and the עבד, eved, which one should be more linked
that the payment should be more linked to the stoning of the
ox? What would you say? This is a question? This is the
case, כופר kofer and עבד, eved, and שלושים שקלים shloshim shekalim of
the עבד. eved.
כופר kofer for בן חורין ben chorin and שלושים שקלים shloshim shekalim
for an עבד. eved. Which one of those, if they were... if
we're going to link one of those to the goring of the
ox, which one?
Any thoughts? כופר? kofer? What? I would say כופר. kofer. Because כופר
kofer means it's a כפרה. kapara. You're חייב מיתה, chayav mita, to
some degree you're li... it's not just damages. To some degree, right,
it's actually like... it's a pseudo killing the person through your ox.
Okay? But it's like ממון mamon though... if you say it's כפרה...
kapara... what? במקום סקילה bimkom sekila of the person. Right. So that's
why I mean... I'm not saying... right. That's why I would think
that only in a case which is seen as a case of
murder where the ox murdered the person where the ox gets סקילה,
sekila, maybe that would be only in those cases would you pay
כופר. kofer. Where שלושים של עבד, shloshim shel eved, okay, is being
paid for damages essentially, right? We never really... essentially, right? We never
really explored that. Where called it כופר, Kofer, it's paid for the
monetary loss. So even if you're not going to gore the ox,
stone the ox, your ox still caused damage to this person's property.
Here's a perfect example. You don't pay שלושים של עבד Shloshim Shel
Eved if the ox gored your own slave, right? It is not
because of the loss of life there, it's because of the loss
of property of the owner of the slave. So that would be
the case I would think would be most unrelated to the stoning
of the ox. But interestingly, until this point, we've been assuming you
can pay כופר Kofer without stoning the ox. That's those are the
cases we discussed a minute ago. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
saying, abba, when it comes to the עבד, eved, okay, at least
he's not contrasting, I'm contrasting him, but he says, when it comes
to the עבד, eved, the פסוק pasuk puts them right together, כסף
שלושים שקלים יתן והשור יסקל, Kesef Shloshim Shekalim Yitein VeHaShor YiSakeil, and
in that case, if you don't stone the ox, you're not going
to pay שלושים של עבד. Shloshim Shel Eved. Yes. Do you find
it disturbing that in these cases of נזק nezek the עבד eved
is treated as property? Of course it's disturbing. Yes. It's profoundly disturbing.
Yes. Okay, but thank you for saying that explicitly. Yes. We mentioned
explicitly yesterday about the is it a קולא kula or is it
a חומרא? humra? We had the whole question. About עבד, eved, right?
30. And we said it's a קצבה, kitzba, there's I'm sorry, it's
just a קצבה, kitzba, it's just it's arbitrary. Right. So it's not
related it's not related in any sense to, I mean, it's not
related in any sense to even נזק. nezek.
Right, but it's not related to the body of the שור. shor.
Right, right. That's true. Yes. Oh, I see. So it even is
more detached in that way. Right, right. That's true from that payment
perspective. Right. Okay. Or if the ox had no intention of killing,
it tried to kill an animal and accidentally killed a slave. And
that's not goring this slave, it's actually just killing it by accident.
Yeah, it might have tried to kill something else, but it wound
up killing the slave. That's like we had before. It tried to
kill an animal and instead accidentally killed the slave. Okay. Okay.
שנאמר shene'emar, כסף שלושים שקלים יתן לאדוניו והשור יסקל. kesef shloshim shekalim
yitein l'adonav v'ha-shor yisakeil. כל זמן שהשור בסקילה הבעל משלם שלושים שקלים.
Kol zman she'ha'shor b'sekilah ha'ba'al meshalem shloshim shekalim. If you stone the
ox, you pay 30.
אין השור בסקילה אין הבעל משלם שלושים שקלים. Ein ha'shor b'sekilah ein
ha'ba'al meshalem shloshim shekalim. But if you don't stone the ox, you
don't pay 30. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now so again, we start
with the עבד eved case. That seems more obvious based on the
פסוק. pasuk. Less obvious based on the logic, but more obvious based
on the פסוק. pasuk. אמר רבא שור שהמית בן חורין. Amar Rava
Shor SheHeimit Ben Chorin. Great. Now let's apply that to a case
of כופר. Kofer. If an ox gores a free
person שלא בכוונה, shelo b'kavana, פטור מכופר. patur mi'kofer. Exempt from כופר,
Kofer, again, against things we were saying earlier. שנאמר השור יסקל וגם
בעליו יומת אם כופר יושת עליו ונתן פדיון נפשו ככל אשר יושת
עליו. Shene'emar HaShor YiSakeil VeGam Be'Alav Yummat Im Kofer Yushas Alav VeNatan
Pidyon Nafsho KeKol Asher Yushas Alav.
Now that is not nearly as closely juxtaposed as the case of
עבד. eved. You got a lot of words between them. But nevertheless,
it says stone the ox and then pay the כופר. Kofer. So
therefore, there it's also combined. כל זמן שהשור בסקילה הבעל משלם כופר.
Kol zman she'ha'shor b'sekilah ha'ba'al meshalem kofer.
If you stone the ox, you pay your כופר. Kofer. אין השור
בסקילה, Ein ha'shor b'sekilah, if it's going to be a scenario you
don't stone the ox, you don't pay כופר. Kofer. I understand, but
it's not like literally like the exact next phrase. No, it's not
השור יסקל והכופר ישית עליו. HaShor YiSakeil VeHaKofer Yashit Alav. השור יסקל
וגם בעליו יומת. HaShor YiSakeil VeGam Be'Alav Yummat.
I know, Michael, it is not as closely juxtaposed as כסף שלושים
שקלים יתן והשור יסקל. Kesef Shloshim Shekalim Yitein VeHaShor YiSakeil. You got
the two verbs there, one word away from each other. Okay, it's
much more distant here. Okay. אין השור בסקילה אין הבעל משלם כופר.
Ein ha'shor b'sekilah ein ha'ba'al meshalem kofer. But if you're not going
to stone the ox, you're not going to pay כופר. Kofer. Okay?
So we said it by the so that, as we said, makes
more logical sense, but in the גמרא, Gemara, that's stage two and
in the פסוקים, Psukim, it's less closely juxtaposed. Okay. איתיבי אביי. Eiseiv
Abaye. אביי Abaye will ask you asks. המית שורי פלוני או שורו
של פלוני. Heimit shorei ploni o shoro shel ploni.
Somebody admits, right? So you're מודה, modeh, you don't have witnesses. My
ox killed somebody or killed somebody's ox. הרי זה משלם על פי
עצמו. Harei zeh meshalem al pi atzmo. You pay based on your
own admission. You're not a מודה בקנס. modeh b'knas. If you say
my ox killed an ox, then you're מודה בממון. modeh b'mamon. So
you know, the admission of an owner in terms of a monetary
debt is כמאה עדים. k'meia eidim. If you're מודה בכופר, modeh b'kofer,
כופר Kofer isn't קנס. knas. כופר Kofer is כפרה. kapara. So it's
like you're מודה modeh that you have to bring a קרבן. korban.
Like I did a sin, I have to bring a קרבן חטאת.
korban chatat. Okay? So in those cases, you pay. Okay. הרי זה
משלם על פי עצמו. Harei zeh meshalem al pi atzmo. מאי לאו
כופר? Mai lav kofer? Ay,
so you see that you're now, but the whole thing is, if
you admit that your ox gored, are you stoning the ox? No,
right? You're not stoning the ox. So you see, here's a case
where you're not stoning the ox and you're paying כופר. Kofer. מאי
לאו כופר? Mai lav kofer? Don't you see you're paying כופר Kofer
without stoning the ox? Because you only stone the ox כמיתת הבעל
כך מיתת השור. k'mitat ha'ba'al kach mitat ha'shor. You only stone the
ox in a scenario you would stone a human being. You need
to have two witnesses. You would not stone the ox based on
somebody's own admission. You need על פי עצמו. al pi atzmo. על
פי עצמו Al pi atzmo is the issue. על פי עצמו. Al
pi atzmo. Okay? So the same way you wouldn't you wouldn't execute
a person based on their own admission, you don't execute an ox
based on the owner's admission. You need to have objective witnesses. Okay?
You treat it like a murder trial. But the אף עצמו af
atzmo though of course should be the owner of the ox. I
understand. Right? So it's an incentive. What? We haven't seen it yet.
Okay, you're right. It's coming up. We haven't seen it yet. Okay,
but it is but it is very, very clear that that's the
case. In an incentive, based on the value of the ox. If
the if your value is more than שלושים שקלים, shloshim shekalim, you'd
You might as well always say
אם שור im shor because otherwise you're paying less by paying the
כופר. kofer. What? What are you talking about? In a questionable case,
right?
You'd rather not have your ox... Sure, you'd rather... Your admission doesn't
get you out of it getting stoned. It just doesn't obligate you.
Okay, so my... I'm admitted into this... Yes, yes, absolutely. Okay, same
way... same way it doesn't get you out of getting executed if
you committed a crime. Okay, right? It's only by קנס kenas that
your admission might get you out of, not by actual execution. Surely
the ox
is an 'ox-ecution'. Okay, alright, very good. Yeah, how long were you
waiting for that? משלם על פי עצמו, meshaleim al pi atzmo, מה
לאו כופר? ma lav kofer? So here you have a case of
admission where you don't have witnesses, so you're not going to stone
the ox. Shhh... You don't have witnesses, you're not going to stone
the ox, but you're going to pay. So you see, you pay
כופר kofer without stoning the ox. The גמרא Gemara says לא דמים.
lo damim. No, in that case you're not going to pay כופר.
kofer. What you are going to pay is monetary compensation. Now this
is a huge, big חידוש chiddush the גמרא Gemara is coming up
with and it's going to stay with us for the rest of
the דף daf to figure it out. If you might remember from
the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, I've been pointing out to you
that even putting ideas of קים ליה kim lei aside, you never
have a monetary compensation for the accidental... for loss of life, for
taking somebody's life. Okay, taking somebody's life is either... it's either רציחה
retzicha or you go into גלות galut or you pay a כופר,
kofer, whatever. But you don't pay a monetary compensation. What the גמרא
Gemara here is saying is that that might not be true if
you didn't kill the person yourself. If you killed the person yourself,
then it's never going to be dealt with in terms of a
civil suit. It is never going to be compensated. But if your
ox kills a person, you might actually be a case where you
pay compensation, not כופר. kofer. And the גמרא Gemara sort of sees
this as like an alternate, as like a fallback position. The first
thing that the תורה Torah says is you pay כופר. kofer. But
in a scenario where you wouldn't pay כופר, kofer, okay, you would
still pay compensation. So what's the scenario? So according to us right
now, the scenario is if you're not going to stone the ox.
And since the כופר kofer is tied in with the stoning of
the ox, so if you're not going to stone the ox, you're
not going to pay כופר, kofer, but you'll still pay monetary compensation.
Which, by the way, makes a lot of sense, right? The כופר
kofer is for being חייב מיתה, chayav mita, and that's only if
you stone the ox. But even if it wasn't so wicked to
be חייב מיתה, chayav mita, you're still... you're still responsible for loss
of life. So there can still be a monetary payment. So what
is this monetary payment? So it's the value of the person's life
on the slave market. So the question becomes, well wait a minute,
isn't that the exact same thing that כופר kofer is? Well, if
כופר kofer is דמי מזיק, damei mazik, it's a different amount. It's
the difference between דמי מזיק damei mazik for כופר kofer and דמי
ניזק damei nizak for ממון. mamon. But if כופר kofer is דמי
ניזק, damei nizak, what's the difference? So look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות
Tosafot says, מה לאו כופר, לא דמים. ma lav kofer, lo damim.
תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar,
למאן דאמר le'man de'amar כופר דמי ניזק, kofer damei nizak, מאי איכא
בין דמים לכופר? mai ika bein damim le'kofer? Either way, you're paying
for the value of the person on the slave market. Who cares
if you call it כופר kofer or you call it or you
call it compensation? ונראה לרי, Venira lari, כגון שמת המזיק, kegon shemet
hamazik, דאין כפרה לאחר מיתה, de'ein kapara le'acher mita, כמו חטאת ואשם
kemo chatat ve'asham דאין באים לאחר מיתה. de'ein ba'im le'acher mita. Let's
say the owner of the ox, of the goring ox, died. If
it's compensation, then his estate still has to pay it out. It's
a debt he had during life. But if it's כפרה, kapara, so
if a person was מחלל שבת, mechaleil Shabbat, you don't bring a
קרבן korban for him after he dies. Okay? אבל דמים משלם. Aval
damim meshaleim. ולפי זה חמורה שלא בכוונה מבכוונה. Ulefi ze chamura shelo
ve'khavana me've'khavana. He says, it's ironic. When you're doing it as כפרה,
kapara, you actually... the liability is less than when you're doing it
as compensation. Okay, but the כפרה kapara aspect comes first. Only when
כפרה kapara isn't... isn't true because like the שור shor doesn't get
סקילה, sekila, then the idea of compensation kicks in.
Only if... only if כופר kofer is דמי מזיק, damei mazik, then
it's always... only if כופר kofer is דמי מזיק, damei mazik, then
there could be differences either way, okay? Sometimes you could be paying
more with כופר, kofer, sometimes you could be paying more with ממון.
mamon. But right, it depends on who's worth more. But if it's
דמי ניזק, damei nizak, you know, then it's... then it's always the
same amount. Why is it not the same? Because whether the... whether
I'm paying כופר kofer as דמי ניזק damei nizak or paying תשלומין
tashlumin as דמי ניזק, damei nizak, it's the same amount of money.
It's דמי ניזק. damei nizak.
If the amount you pay כופר kofer is the guy's worth on
the slave market and the amount you pay compensation is the guy's
worth on the slave market and it's both the same guy, then
you're paying the same amount. But תוספות Tosafot says nevertheless, actually כופר
kofer would... ממון mamon would actually have a more enduring... enduring debt
than כופר. kofer. כופר kofer would only be for the person. ממון
mamon would be on the estate. What if כופר kofer was a
flat amount, not... No, דמי ניזק damei nizak or דמי מזיק. damei
mazik. You're thinking about שלושים של עבד, shloshim shel eved, עבד. eved.
Okay, תוספות, Tosafot, let's skip... let's... why is it... why is it
חמורה שלא בכוונה מבכוונה chamura shelo ve'khavana me've'khavana again?
Because שלא בכוונה shelo ve'khavana would be ממון, mamon, and then it
would be a debt that would last on the estate even after
the guy's death. Okay, if you go two lines down in תוספות
Tosafot you said, ועוד יש לומר דדווקא ממזיק. ve'od yesh lomar dedavka
memazik. ויש לומר דדווקא מיני בין דמים לכופר דדמים יכול למחול וכופר
אין יכול למחול. v'yesh lomar d'davka minei bein damim l'kofer d'damim yachol
limchol v'kofer ein yachol limchol. That's a great idea. Let's say the
surviving family says we waive it, we don't need you to pay.
They could say that if it's compensation, but if it's כפרה kapara
it's like, I'm sorry, you can't waive, I still have to do
this for my atonement. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it eima, here's a third possibility,
דכופר שלם אמר רחמנא ולא חצי כופר. d'kofer shaleim amar rachmana v'lo
chatzi kofer. Remember the case of the שותפין? shutfin? Do we say
each one pays a half or each one pays all? By the
way, the רמב"ם Rambam in that case rules that each one pays
full because it's כפרה, kapara, each person needs a full כפרה. kapara.
So תוספות Tosafot says that's another נפקא מינה, nafka mina, נפקא מינה
נמי להא. nafka mina nami l'ha. So if it was דמים, damim,
they would obviously each only pay a half, the partners of the
ox that killed, because it's ultimately about getting the guy compensated. But
if it's כפרה, kapara, then each one would pay a full amount.
Okay, so fascinating opportunity to look at different conceptual differences between כפרה
kapara and ממון, mamon, כופר kofer and ממון, mamon, but also what's
fascinating is we've been so consistently denying that there's compensation for human
life, and here we're saying actually there would be. In a case
where there's no כופר, kofer, you would actually do compensation. Not when
you kill—when a person kills a person—but when an ox killed a
person. Yes? I don't understand about this כפרה לחיים. kapara l'chaim. When
we say כפרה לחיים ישראל מכאן שמתים צריכים כפרה, kapara l'chaim Yisrael
mikan shemetim tzrichim kapara, so like how does that play—I'm trying to
understand this theologically. Yeah, I don't know the theological answer. I can
tell you the practical answer is is that you don't bring a
קרבן korban for somebody after they die. Right? Whether something you do
can be a כפרה kapara for people, but that's not like an
obligation that that person or his estate has. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so it's sort of like having
a civil case in a murder case? Yeah, that's what I've been
saying all along like the O.J. Simpson. But the point is that
we're still never going to say that according to this at least,
we're never going to say that by case when a human took
a life. But when an ox took a life, okay, then maybe
if it's not—we're not going to do both, כפרה kapara and תשלומין.
tashlumin. We're going to start the same way you always start with
the criminal. Okay, but if we can't do the כפרה kapara in
this case by the ox, we're going to do the תשלומין. tashlumin.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so that's
how we tried to explain, here's how you could have payment even
though you're not stoning the ox.
אי דמים, i damim, one minute, if it's payment compensation, back to
the גמרא Gemara five lines from the bottom, אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
let's look at the end of the ברייתא. braita. הזיק שורו את
עבדו של פלוני אינו משלם על פי עצמו. hizik shoro et avdo
shel ploni eino meshalem al pi atzmo. My ox killed so-and-so's slave,
then that's שלשים שקל shloshim shekel is a קנס, knas, you don't
do it based on your own admission. Okay, ואי דמים, v'i damim,
but one minute, you're not going to stone the ox in that
case because it's on your own admission, so you're not going to
pay the שלשים שקל של עבד shloshim shekel shel eved according to
this logic, but you should be paying דמים, damim, you should be
paying compensation in that case, right? It should follow the same pattern.
If you're not paying the special the arbitrary thing what the תורה
Torah says because you're not going to gore the ox, then we
should fall back to the idea of paying
compensation. הגמרא HaGemara says ואי דמים, v'i damim, if we're dealing with
an idea that you're not goring the ox and we're dealing with
a compensation issue, אמאי לא? amai lo? So you should pay a
compensation of the slave based on your own admission. So אמר ליה
יכילנא לשינויי לך, amar lei yachilna l'shinuyei lach, I could tell you,
רישא דמים וסיפא קנס. reisha damim v'seifa knas. The beginning is talking
about not paying money, and the end is talking about not paying
a קנס. knas. But that's a very weak answer because if we're
talking about that you're not stoning the ox so you're not dealing
with the payments in the תורה, Torah, then they both should be
talking about דמים. damim. And anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
מיהו שינויי דחיקא לא משנינא לך, mihu shinuyei d'chika lo m'shanina lach,
I'm not going to give you what I know is a bad
answer. Okay, obviously they're both talking about the same issue. If the
רישא reisha is talking about paying compensation, that's the end. אידי ואידי
דמים, idi v'idi damim, they're both talking about compensation. מיהו, mihu, says
בין—now we're to explain that this thing we just—this idea we just
introduced that when you're not paying כופר, kofer you're going to pay
דמים damim is true by a בן חורין ben chorin but not
true by a עבד. eved. Now let me ask you about this
because this actually makes sense in a simpler way than the גמרא
Gemara says it. Why do you think by a בן חורין ben
chorin if you don't pay כופר kofer you'll do compensation, but by
a עבד eved if you don't do the שלשים שקל shloshim shekel
in the תורה Torah because the שור shor isn't gored—isn't stoned—you would
not pay compensation? Do you see how like it would make more
sense to say that there would be a fall back to pay
compensation by a בן חורין ben chorin but not by the case
by the עבד? eved? Any thoughts about that? By a בן חורין,
ben chorin, if you don't pay the כופר kofer, because you're not
stoning the ox, the גמרא's Gemara going to say there would be
a monetary payment to be paid. But by the עבד, eved, if
you're not going to pay the שלשים שקל, shloshim shekel, there would
not be a compensation to be paid. The גמרא Gemara will explain
it in a minute, but I think it makes a lot of
sense, because the שלשים שקל shloshim shekel of the עבד eved is
the monetary payment. So why should you say, oh, if you don't
pay the arbitrary
monetary payment the תורה Torah assigned, that's the end of it? Right?
But by the בן חורין, ben chorin, if you're not doing the
כופר, Kofer you're not doing the criminal thing, then we can move
on to the monetary payment. So that makes sense, but let's see
now how the גמרא Gemara explains it. מיהו בן חורין דמשלם כופר
על פי עצמו, mihu ben chorin d'meshalem kofer al pi atzmo, there
could be a case where In the case of a free person,
you will pay כופר Kofer based on your own admission. How could
that be possible if you can only pay כופר Kofer? if the
ox is going to be stoned, and you don't stone the ox
based on the person's admission? By the following case: היכי דמי, Heichi
Dami, what's the case? דאתו סהדי ואסהידו ביה דקטל, De'asu Sahadi Ve'ashidu
Bei Dekatul, when
witnesses came and testified that this ox gored and killed somebody, ולא
ידעי אי תם הוא אי מועד הוא, Velo Yadai Ei Tam Hava
Ei Muad Hava, but they don't know if it's a תם Tam
or it's a מועד. Muad. So right now, witnesses say it killed
somebody, but we don't know תם Tam or מועד. Muad. What would
be the הלכה Halacha right now? What would you do to the
ox? Stone it, because you stone an ox whether it's a תם
Tam or a מועד. Muad. Would you pay כופר? Kofer
No, because you don't know it's a מועד. Muad. Everybody with me
here? The ox killed, so you're with witnesses, because there are witnesses
you're going to stone the ox, but you're not going to pay
כופר Kofer because you don't know if it's a תם Tam or
מועד. Muad. דאמר, De'amar, okay, מרי, Mari, and the master
says דמועד הוא, Demuad Hu, oh, you know what? I'll admit it,
it's a מועד. Muad. דמשלם כופר על פי עצמו, Demeshalem Kofer Al
Pi Atzmo, you're going to pay כופר Kofer? on your own admission.
Why will you be paying כופר? Kofer Because the ox will be
stoned, because witnesses already testified that the ox was going to be
stoned, and your admission made you pay כופר Kofer because you admitted
it was a מועד. Muad. Right, he's motivated to.
There you go. And כופר Kofer is not a קנס. Knas. Okay.
Therefore, since there are cases by
an ox where you will pay כופר Kofer on your own admission,
so היכא דליכא סהדי, Heicha Delieka Sahadi, even if there are no
witnesses and there's not going to be a כפרה, Kapara, משלם דמים,
Meshalem Damin,
at least you'll pay money. Meaning, somehow your own admission can obligate
you in כופר Kofer, by an ox in certain scenarios. So it
has the power also to obligate you to pay money when there
are no witnesses. לגבי עבד, Legabi Eved, by a slave, שאינו משלם
קנס על פי עצמו, She'eino Meshalem Knas Al Pi Atzmo, you can
never pay the קנס Knas by an עבד Eved on your own
admission, because it's always a מודה בקנס. Modeh Beknas. Okay. והיכי דמי?
Veheichi Dami? דאתו עדים ואסהידו ביה דקטל. De'asu Eidim Ve'ashidu Bei Dekatul.
If witnesses testify that the ox gored, ולא ידעי אי תם הוא
אי מועד הוא, Velo Yadai Ei Tam Hava Ei Muad Hava, but
we don't know תם Tam or מועד, Muad, ואמר מרי מועד הוא,
Ve'amar Mari Muad Hu, and you admit that it was a מועד,
Muad, לא משלם קנס על פי עצמו, Lo Meshalem Knas Al Pi
Atzmo, you'll never pay it, even if you're stoning the ox, you're
never going to pay the קנס על פי עצמו. Knas Al Pi
Atzmo. So since your own admission never has the power to obligate
you in the prime payment that the תורה Torah describes, so therefore
היכא דליכא עדים, Heicha Delieka Eidim, if there are no witnesses, לא
משלם דמים, Lo Meshalem Damin, you wouldn't pay money. So to me,
I don't really get the connection, but whatever. To me the logic
makes a lot more sense this difference for the reason we said.
But the גמרא Gemara said by כופר, Kofer, since your admission in
some scenarios can obligate you, then even when there's not going to
be כפרה כופר, Kapara Kofer, there'll be דמים. Damin. By עבד, Eved,
your admission will never obligate you in the שלשים, Shloshim, so therefore
there will never be דמים Damin by your own admission. Okay. Whatever.
Anyway, that's how we're now explaining it. There is דמים Damin to
be paid when you're not doing the כופר, Kofer, when you're not
doing the whatever, when you're not doing the כופר, Kofer there is
דמים Damin to be paid, but the כופר Kofer, will only be
when the ox is gored. Similarly, by the way, presumably here the
difference was emphasized in terms of the guy's own admission. If the
ox gores an עבד Eved שלא בכוונה Shelo Bechavana and we're saying
you're not paying שלשים שקל, Shloshim Shekel, presumably if we have witnesses
to that, maybe you would still pay דמים Damin by the
עבד. Eved. Right? Everybody's with me here? The גמרא Gemara made a
difference between whether your own admission can obligate you in דמים Damin
by an עבד Eved or free person. But what the גמרא Gemara
has introduced is number one, that all these payments, the payments in
the תורה Torah are linked to stoning the ox, and number two,
that underlying them is a possibility to be paying compensation. And the
same way that's true by a בן חורין, Ben Chorin, presumably it
could be true by an עבד Eved too if there are witnesses
that the ox gored שלא בכוונה. Shelo Bechavana. Alright, so now we've
introduced a lot of new ideas. Now the גמרא Gemara moves on.
Okay, where were we? מותיב רב שמואל בר רב יצחק. Motiv Rav
Shmuel Bar Rav Yitzchak. כל שחייב בבן חורין חייב בעבד. Kol Shechayav
Beven Chorin Chayav Be'eved. We have a ברייתא Braita that says anytime
you have to pay by a free person, you pay by a
slave. בין בכופר בין במיתה, Bein Bekofer Bein Bemisa, whether you're paying
the כופר, Kofer whether you're goring the ox. So the גמרא Gemara
says כופר בעבד מי איכא? Kofer Be'eved Mi Ika? Wait a minute,
you never pay כופר Kofer by a slave. What does it mean?
אלא לאו דמים? Ella Lav Damin? It must be money. So here
again, we're saying there would be an idea of compensation, whether in
the case of עבד Eved or in the case of a בן
חורין. Ben Chorin. And we're saying whenever you would pay one, you
would pay the other. Whenever you would pay for a בן חורין,
Ben Chorin, you pay for an עבד. Eved. So if by your
own admission you would pay compensation for a בן חורין Ben Chorin
because you're not paying כופר Kofer, by your own admission or whatever,
you're not stoning the ox, you would also pay compensation by an
עבד. Eved. Okay, so we don't have—we've been trying to say there's
a difference, your own admission would obligate you by a בן חורין
Ben Chorin and not by an עבד, Eved, here it says it's
the same. איכא דאמרי הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. Ika De'amri
Hu Motiv Lah Vehu Mefarek Lah. Some say he asked the question
and he gave the answer. איכא דאמרי, Ika De'amri, אמר ליה רבא
Amar Lei Rava answered it for him. הכי קתני, Hachi Katani, no,
no, here's how to read that ברייתא. Braita. כל שחייב בבן חורין
בכוונה על פי עדים כופר. Kol Shechayav Beven Chorin Bechavana Al Pi
Eidim Kofer. Anytime you would pay by a free person כופר, Kofer?
when would you pay by a free person כופר? kofer, There were
witnesses and... was with בכוונה. bekavana. In that case, חייב בעבד קנס.
chayav be'eved knas. That was the parallel case you would pay קנס
knas for an עבד. eved. They had to be witnesses and they
had to be בכוונה. bekavana. וכל שחייב בבן חורין שלא בכוונה על
פי עדים דמים, Vekol shechayav beven chorin shelo bekavana al pi edim
domim, and if you would pay by a free person, you would
pay you would pay you would pay compensation, how would you with
witnesses? What would be a case you pay compensation with witnesses? That
the act is שלא בכוונה. shelo bekavana. So you're not going to
stone the ox, you're still going to pay compensation. בכוונה שלא בכוונה
Bekavana shelo bekavana is not the same as תם ומועד? tam umuad?
Correct. An ox is only חייב chayav if it gets stoned, it
gets stoned if it's a תם tam but only if it kills
the person בכוונה. bekavana. Right. Yeah, working it through. So if it's
a תם tam and there are witnesses and it killed the person
but accidentally, you don't there's no סקילה skila for it. Right. Right.
סקילה Skila regardless of תם tam or מועד muad but it requires
כוונה. kavana. Okay. So חייב בעבד שלא בכוונה על פי עדים דמים.
chayav be'eved shelo bekavana al pi edim domim. Okay. So therefore by
the slave too, if you're not going to pay the שלושים, shloshim,
you're going to pay the דמים domim because in a case when
you have witnesses. So what we are saying is it's getting I
know a little complicated, maybe I should try to use this. Okay,
here's what we're saying. Okay, the Torah says סקילה skila כופר, kofer
okay this is בן חורין, ben chorin, right? It's a סקילה skila
and כופר kofer. and by עבד eved it says סקילה skila and
שלושים shloshim and we are saying that they are linked. Okay, when
you get one you only get the other. Okay. So in a
case of no witnesses which means no סקילה. skila. No סקילה, skila,
okay so therefore there's going to be no כופר. kofer, No כופר,
kofer, but there's going to be דמים. domim. We've introduced this new
idea of דמים domim by a free person. By the עבד, eved,
there's going to be no שלושים, shloshim, I'm sorry, no, we've already
decided no סקילה, skila, let me write it like this. I'm going
to make you know what, let me write it like this. There'll
be no סקילה skila because there's no witnesses. So therefore no כופר,
kofer okay but there will be דמים. domim. And here too, there'll
be no סקילה skila because of no witnesses and therefore no שלושים
shloshim but there will be דמים. domim. Which is quite interesting, rather
than paying thirty as an arbitrary price, you're now going to pay
a you know a real price of compensation. That's in the case
of no witnesses, okay. So so in the case of witnesses... no
witnesses but you admit... שלא בכוונה, shelo bekavana, right, oh good point,
but the point is here, ah ah your good point here. No
witnesses but you admit, okay, so you're מודה, modeh, okay. So actually
logically you should be paying דמים, domim, thank you, I'd forgotten that
that was the גמרא's Gemara question, but it said no דמים domim
because your own admission is weaker here since this is a case
of קנס, knas, fundamentally we have a case of קנס, knas, your
own admission your own admission can't מחייב mechayev you. Can't obligate. Okay,
since it starts from a case of קנס. knas. So that's what's
complicated the גמרא. Gemara. It said shouldn't you pay דמים domim here?
Said, well, since you can never obligate yourself in the base in
the קנס, knas, your own admission can't can't obligate you here either,
even though this is a case of דמים. domim. That was the
חידוש chidush of the גמרא. Gemara. But in case of witnesses... what...
that's for slave... what... that's for slave right and this is free
person. Compensation you would pay. Yeah דמים domim you would pay על
פי עצמו, al pi atzmo, right, okay, so witnesses שלא בכוונה shelo
bekavana also no סקילה skila but there are witnesses. So no סקילה
skila no כופר kofer and yes דמים. domim. And here right no
סקילה skila because of no witnesses and therefore no שלושים shloshim but
yes דמים. domim. Okay, here you would do דמים domim because here
it doesn't need to be your admission. If the witness here is
your admission can't obligate you because it doesn't obligate you in the
base case of the קנס. knas. So your admission can't obligate you
in the דמים. domim. Okay, but here you will be pay in
these cases you will be paying the דמים, domim, all right. Because
it's not על פי עצמו. al pi atzmo. All right. So basically
the גמרא's Gemara introduced there's this new idea called תשלומין tashlumin which
becomes the fallback when you cannot pay the payment in the Torah.
Okay and it would be true by עבד eved and it would
be true by בן חורין ben chorin and the only exception is
the case of your own admission because the case of your own
admission. isn't powerful enough to make you pay by עבד eved because
you would never pay the base קנס knas by the case of
your own admission. All right, so let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, so וקסבר בן חורין שלא בכוונה
על פי עדים דמים, v'kasvar ben chorin shelo b'kavana al pi eidim
damim, if you're going to pay compensation when it was with witnesses
without כוונה, kavana, בעבד b'eved so also חייב בעבד שלא בכוונה על
פי עדים דמים. chayav b'eved shelo b'kavana al pi eidim damim. By
the case of a slave too, there are witnesses, it's שלא בכוונה,
shelo b'kavana, you don't stone the שור, shor, you don't pay the
שלושים, shloshim, you will pay the compensation. אמר ליה רבא אי הכי,
amar lei Rava ei hachi, if that's true, this is great, we've
now introduced this new idea of paying compensation for a human life
in a case where you're not doing the initial payment in the
תורה. Torah. So if that's true about an ox, what about the
other אבות נזיקין? avos nezikin? What about fire? What about a well?
Well, you already know the answer about a well because it's שור
ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים. shor v'lo adam chamor v'lo kelim. Humans
are exempt by the case of the well if you remember that,
the death of a human. But what about a fire? Would you
pay תשלומין tashlumin if a fire takes a human life? Great question.
אמר ליה רבא אי הכי אשו שלא בכוונה על פי עדים נשלם
דמים. amar lei Rava ei hachi isho shelo b'kavana al pi eidim
nishalem damim. Let's say your fire שלא בכוונה shelo b'kavana with witnesses
you should pay. Now what does he mean שלא בכוונה? shelo b'kavana?
תוספות Tosafos says it's לאו דווקא, lav davka, we're assuming here אשו
isho is משום ממונו, mishum mamono, לא משום חציו. lo mishum chitzav.
And if it's משום ממונו, mishum mamono, if it's a type of
property of yours that damages, then the same way when your ox
takes a life if you're paying תשלומין, tashlumin, when your fire takes
a life even if it is בכוונה b'kavana because the whole reason
you need it שלא בכוונה shelo b'kavana by the ox was to
get it out of the כופר kofer case. But by אש eish
there's no כופר kofer by אש, eish, right? That's worth taking a
moment to appreciate. Your ox you've seen is liable, fundamentally deserving of
death, you're going to pay a כפרה, kaparah, your fire you would
think you have more liability for and the תורה Torah never has
a כופר kofer. for your fire. Your fire accidentally takes a life.
So for your fire there's never כופר. kofer At least you should
pay compensation, at least you should pay תשלומין. tashlumin. Okay, is that
true or not? ומנא ליה לרבא דלא משלם, u'mena lei l'Rava d'lo
mishalem, why was Rava saying oh if that's true then you would
wind up doing that? Maybe you should. Why does he take it
for granted that you don't pay when your fire takes a life?
Okay, אילימא מדקא תני ותני במתניתין, ee'leima mid'ka tani v'tani b'matnitin, we
learned in the משנה, Mishna, הגדי כפות לו ועבד סמוך לו, hagdi
kafut lo v'eved samuch lo, you might remember this case. You have
a bound up goat and a slave that's not bound standing next
to a stack of grain, ונסרף עמו, v'nisraf imo, they were all
burnt with a fire that you let forth. חייב, chayav, you're חייב
chayav why? You have to pay for the goat because it couldn't
run away, so obviously you're paying for אש. eish. You're not going
to... the עבד eved could have run away, so you're not going
to say קים ליה kim lei or whatever, you're not going to
be חייב chayav for the עבד. eved. You're basically חייב chayav in
that case for the goat. עבד כפות לו וגדי סמוך לו, eved
kafut lo v'gdi samuch lo, now if the עבד eved was bound
and the goat was nearby but not bound, ונסרף עמו פטור, v'nisraf
imo patur, you're going to be פטור, patur, פטור patur from, you
might be פטור patur even for the grain because of קים ליה,
kim lei, that's a separate question about that. But anyway right now
we're focusing on the idea that you're פטור patur for the slave.
So we're assuming why are you פטור patur for the slave? It's
your fire, your fire took a human life. Well because the תורה
Torah never has כופר kofer by a fire and presumably we think
it doesn't have compensation for a human life. Now that's interesting. It
wouldn't even have compensation for a human life of a slave which
we could just as easily look at as property, not look at
as life. But Rava's now saying why aren't you going to pay
דמים damim here? Right? It seems like you're not going to pay
compensation for a human life out of those special cases in the
תורה. Torah. You're saying you're not paying compensation for a piece of
property, that's the... that's why you see even a bigger חידוש, chiddush,
so how much more so should you... disturbing, but I understand. So
but it shows you there's never compensation for a human life. Okay,
so how could you say it's true here? It's not true over
there by the fire case. אמר ריש לקיש כגון שהצית בגופו של
עבד קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, amar Resh Lakish k'gon she'hitzis b'gufo shel
eved kim lei bid'rabba minei, no, no, no, that's not that your
fire escaped, that's that you directly put your torch against the slave,
you murdered the slave, so you're not paying because of קים ליה.
kim lei. Okay, but if your fire escaped and took a human
life you would pay ממון. mamon. Yes, there's no כופר kofer by
fire, there is ממון. mamon. ואלא מהא, v'ela mei'ha, one, so here's
why Rava thinks that it's not possible by the case of fire.
דתניא, detanya, we turned a ברייתא, Baraita, חומר באש מבור, chomer b'eish
mibbor, an אש eish is more weightier than a בור bor in
the case of stringent, שאש מועדת לאכול בין דבר הראוי לו בין
דבר שאינו ראוי לו, she'eish muedes le'echol bein davar harauy lo bein
davar she'eino rauy lo, a fire is considered liable when it destroys
things that are fit for it or not fit for it. Remember
the not fit for it is like when it scorches grass, whatever,
that's an abnormal thing you make a fire out of or whatever.
מה שאין כן בבור, ma she'ein ken b'bor, but a pit is
פטור, patur, it's פטור patur by כלים, kelim, it's פטור patur by
people falling into it, it's פטור patur by certain things that are
seen to be not normal. So that's the way in which a
fire is weightier. So why? The גמרא Gemara says, but you had
a great, why did it go to that example? There was a
much better example if what you're saying is true. The אילו שאש
משלם שלא בכוונה דמי מה שאין כן בבור לא תני. Ilu she'eish
mishallem shelo bekavana dami mah she'ein ken be'vor lo tana. It should
have said, by fire, you pay compensation for human life, by a
well you don't, because the well we have the דרשה drasha שור
ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים. shor velo adam chamor velo keilim. We
know that a human life is fundamentally excluded by the case of
the well. But if by a fire there is that compensation, that
should have been a simple, powerful difference between fire and well, whether
you would ever compensate a human life. So the גמרא's Gemara answer
is תנא ושיער. tana veshayar. Ah, fine, it was not a complete
list, which is a very unsatisfactory answer. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says there's no proof that you don't pay compensation by fire. Why
does רבא Rava take it for granted that you don't? So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא רבא גופיה איבעיא מיבעיא ליה. ella Rava gufei
iba'i mi'ba'ei lei. No, no, you misunderstood רבא. Rava. When רבא Rava
said oh, so then a fire should be paying for a human
life, it was all in the tone of voice. He wasn't saying
it as like astounded and challenging. It was a question: Oh, so
you're saying that a fire should be paying for a human life?
You see how much the tone of voice makes a difference. So
רבא Rava was asking this as a question, not as a challenge.
אש שלא בכוונה מי משלם דמי או לא? eish shelo bekavana mi
mishallem dami o lo? Now that you're telling me there's an idea
of compensation by an ox for human life, what about a fire?
מי אמרינן גבי שור הוא דבכוונה משלם כופר שלא בכוונה משלם דמי?
mi amrinan gabei shor hu dibe'kavana mishallem kofer shelo bekavana mishallem dami?
Maybe by an ox the תורה Torah starts by telling you there's
going to be a type of a payment, a כופר kofer, payment.
Then we can say once the תורה Torah has told you there'll
be a payment for life, if you don't pay כופר, kofer. then
you'll pay compensation. But at least we started with the תורה Torah
telling me there is a payment. אבל אש דבכוונה לא משלם כופר.
aval eish dibe'kavana lo mishallem kofer. Fire with בכוונה bekavana you don't
pay כופר. kofer Now again, what does it mean בכוונה? bekavana? You
could just say it means you never pay כופר kofer by אש.
eish. The תורה Torah never said כופר kofer by אש. eish. רש"י
Rashi also says here בכוונה bekavana means that you intentionally, like, you
know, burned somebody, you murdered somebody. Okay, but that's, but we're talking
even in the case where you didn't directly, like, light somebody of
fire. Your fire escapes, okay, but even if there was some בכוונה,
bekavana, if you didn't directly torch somebody, there's never going to be
כופר kofer by אש. eish. The תורה Torah never told you כופר
kofer by אש. eish. So since there's never כופר kofer, by אש,
eish, שלא בכוונה נמי לא משלם דמי. shelo bekavana nami lo mishallem
dami. So maybe once the תורה Torah doesn't have כופר, kofer. maybe
for whatever reason אש eish is excluded from any type of a
payment, even compensation. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say, כיון
דגבי שור שלא בכוונה אף על גב דליכא כופר משלם דמי? keivan
degabei shor shelo bekavana af al gav deleika kofer mishallem dami? Let's
not start with כופר. kofer, Let's just start, forget כופר, kofer let's
just start with the basic case of the ox paying compensation. An
ox without בכוונה, bekavana, אף על גב דליכא כופר, af al gav
deleika kofer, in that case of an ox שלא בכוונה, shelo bekavana,
there's no כופר kofer, in that case. It's שלא בכוונה. shelo bekavana.
So it has nothing to do with כופר, kofer. and we say
משלם דמי, mishallem dami, that an ox pays compensation in cases where
there's no כופר. kofer גבי אש נמי אף על גב דבכוונה לא
משלם כופר שלא בכוונה נמי לישלם דמי? gabei eish nami af al
gav debikavana lo mishallem kofer shelo bekavana nami lishallem dami? By fire
as well, even though the תורה Torah never has כופר kofer by
fire, שלא בכוונה, shelo bekavana, let's at least pay compensation by a
fire. לא ידינן, lo yedinan, and we don't know. תיקו, teiku, and
we leave it as unresolved. Now the funny thing about all this
is, everybody, and it's like we got this by you didn't notice
it, we have no scriptural basis to say that there's דמי dami
by the case of שור שלא בכוונה. shor shelo bekavana. The only
thing the תורה Torah has is כופר kofer, and שלושים. shloshim. The
גמרא, Gemara, to deal with the problem in a ברייתא braita because
you're saying if you're not going to stone the ox, you're not
going to do כופר, kofer you're not going to do this, but
the ברייתא braita says you pay, the גמרא Gemara introduces out of
nowhere the idea that there's going to be monetary payment. And then
we're saying, oh, can we learn fire from ox? You made the
whole thing up to begin with. I mean maybe it's true, but
I'm just saying, it's not like there's any פסוק passuk that tells
you that there's compensation for human life by the case of ox.
So this גמרא Gemara is like huge idea. We've been talking about
כופר kofer and שלושים, shloshim, etc. The גמרא Gemara puts on the
table that when you're not paying those payments in the תורה, Torah,
there will still be compensation for loss of human life. And as
תוספות Tosfos points out, that might be the same amount as כופר
but might have significant different ways of conceptualizing it. And then it
says and that might not be limited to the case of an
ox, it might be true by the case of fire as well,
right? So even if by,
when a human being causes loss of life directly there's no compensation,
when property causes loss of life, that's the question that we that
we have here that we haven't like really fully worked out the
parameters. Okay, so we will pick up with more of this tomorrow.